Guide to the Chauncey Booth Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Chauncey Booth papers
1808-1844
RG 281
Yale University Divinity School Library
5
(12 boxes)
The papers consist primarily of the sermons from Booth's pastoral career in South Coventry, Connecticut from 1815 to 1844.
Booth, Chauncey, 1783-1851
Biographical / Historical
Chauncey Booth was born in East Windsor, Connecticut, on March 15, 1783. He graduated from Yale College in 1810 and from Andover Theological Seminary in 1813. After completion of his theological training, he spent a brief period of time in Bridgewater, New Hampshire, where he engaged in missionary work.
On September 20, 1815, he was ordained and installed as pastor of the Congregational Church in South Coventry, Connecticut. His ministry was characterized by several periods of spiritual revival during which almost 300 persons were received into church membership. He remained as pastor until 1844, when he requested dismission because of ill health. His health continued to deteriorate over the next several years; and he died in South Coventry on May 24, 1851.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Andover Newton Theological School, 2017. Donated to Andover Newton Theological School by Booth and Dimock Library, South Coventry, Connecticut in 1953.
Scope and Contents
The Chauncey Booth Papers, 1808-1844, are primarily the sermons of Booth's entire pastoral career in South Coventry, Connecticut. The sermons are arranged chronologically; undated sermons are arranged according to Biblical text. There is an index to the sermons.
In addition, there is a small number of items that document Booth's academic work. Included in this material are lecture notes and brief compositions. There is no itemization of the compositions, most of which are fragments which cannot be identified by title.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in two series:
Series I. Sermons
Series II. Lecture Notes and Compositions
Congregationalists -- Connecticut; Clergy -- Connecticut; Sermons, American -- 19th century; Booth, Chauncey, 1783-1851
- Sermons, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  See first folder of collection for list of texts for sermons arranged by text, and dates and texts for sermons arranged by date, and full index of sermons by text.
  - Arranged by text
    - Genesis 13:7-9 through Revelation 19:6 (Box 1)
  - Arranged by date
    - 1813 September - 1815 September, 1813–1815 (Box 1)
    - 1815 October - 1816 September, 1815–1816 (Box 2)
    - 1816 November - 1818 May, 1816–1818 (Box 3)
    - 1818 August - 1820 April, 1818–1820 (Box 4)
    - 1820 May - 1821 December, 1820–1821 (Box 5)
    - 1822 January - 1824 April, 1822–1824 (Box 6)
    - 1824 May - 1826 July, 1824–1826 (Box 7)
    - 1826 August - 1830 December, 1826–1830 (Box 8)
    - 1831 January - 1835 July, 1831–1835 (Box 9)
    - 1836 April - 1839 December, 1836–1839 (Box 10)
    - 1840 January - 1844 March, 1840–1844 (Box 11)
  - Sermon notes
    - Notes from Dr. Dwight's sermon, 1808 November 27 (Box 11)
    - Notes from Professor Fitch's sermons, 1822 November 10, 17 (Box 11)
- Lecture Notes and Compositions, Series II
  - Lecture notes
    - Notes on chemistry, vol. 1, 1808 November (Box 12)
    - Notes on chemistry, vol. 2, 1809 March (Box 12)
  - Compositions
    - 41 uncataloged items (Box 12)